My name is Amit and 18 months ago I had another job at Google and I pitched this idea of doing
something with museums and art to my boss who is actually here and she allowed me to
do it. It took 18 months, a lot of fun negotiations and stories I can tell you with 17 very interesting
museums from 9 countries but I'm going to focus on the demo. There are a lot of stories
about why we did this. I think my personal story is explained very simply in the slide
and it's access. I grew up in India, had a great education, not complaining, but I didn't
have access to a lot of these museums and these artworks. When I started traveling and
going to these museums I started learning a lot and while working at Google I tried
to put this desire to make it more accessible with technology together. So we formed a team,
a great team of people and we started doing this. I'm going to probably get into the demo
and then tell you a couple of the interesting things we've had since launch. So simple,
you come to googleartproject.com, you look around all these museums here, you've got
the Uffizi, you've got the MoMA, the Hermitage, the Rikes, the Van Gogh. I'm going to actually
get to one of my favorites, the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York. Two ways of going
in, very simple, click and bang, you're in this museum, doesn't matter where you are,
Bombay, Mexico, doesn't really matter. You move around, you have fun, you want to navigate
around the museum, open the plan up and in one click jump. You're in there, you want
to go to the end of the corridor, keep going, have fun, explore. Thanks, I haven't come
to the best part. So now I'm in front of one of my favorite paintings, The Harvesters by
Peter Bruegel at the Met. I see this plus sign, if the museum has given us the image,
you click on it. Now this is one of the images, so this is all the metadata information for
those of you who are truly interested in art, you can click this, but I'm going to
click this off right now. This is one of these images that we captured in what we call gigapixel
technology. This image, for example, has close to I think around 10 billion pixels. I get
a lot of people asking me, what do you get for 10 billion pixels? I'm going to try and
show you what you really get for 10 billion pixels. You can zoom around very simply, you
see some fun stuff happening here. I love this guy, his expression is priceless. But
then you really want to go deep. And so I started playing around, and I found something
going on over here. And I was like, hold on, that sounds interesting. Went in, and I started
noticing that these kids were actually beating something. I did a little research, spoke
to a couple of my contacts at the Met, and I actually found out that this is a game called
Skull, which involves beating a goose with a stick on Shrove Tuesday. And apparently
it was quite popular. I don't know why they did it, but you know, I learned something
about it. Now, just, you know, we're really deep in, you can really get the cracks. Now
just to give you some perspective, I'm going to zoom out so you really see what you get.
Here is where we were, and this is the painting. So, the best is yet to come, so in a second.
So now, let's just quickly jump into the MoMA, again in New York. So, another one of my favorites,
the Starry Night. Now, the example I showed you was all about finding details. But what
if you want to see brush strokes? And what if you want to see, you know, how Van Gogh
actually created this masterpiece? You zoom in, you really go in, I'm going to go to one
of my favorite parts in this painting, and I'm really going to get to the cracks. This
is the Starry Night, I think, you know, never seen like this before. I'm going to show you
my other favorite feature. There's a lot of other stuff here, but I don't have time.
This is the real cool part. It's called Collections. Any one of you, anybody, doesn't matter if
you're rich, if you're poor, if you have, you know, a fancy, you know, house, doesn't
matter. You can go and create your own museum online, create your own collection across
all these images. Very simply, you go in, and I've created this called The Power of
Zoom. You can just zoom around. This is the Ambassadors, based in the National Gallery.
You can annotate the stuff, send it to your friends, and really get a conversation going
about what you're feeling when you go through these masterpieces. So I think in conclusion,
for me, the main thing is that all the amazing stuff here does not really come from Google.
It doesn't, in my opinion, even come from the museums. Probably shouldn't say that.
It really comes from these artists. And, you know, that's been my humbling experience in
this. I mean, I hope in this digital medium that we do justice to their artwork and represent
it properly online. And the biggest question I get asked nowadays is, did you do this to
replicate the experience of going to a museum? And the answer is no. It's to supplement the
experience. And that's it. Thank you.